r. Florian **Müll**

POSTDOCTORAL HUMAN-COMPUTER INTERACTION RESEARCHER · AR/VR ENTHUSIAST · STATISTICS NERD

Hochschulstraße 10, 64289 Darmstadt, Germany

□ (+49) 1575 6626997 | ▼ f_m@outlook.com | 匝 florian-mueller-darmstadt | 🎓 Publications@Google Scholar



Summary

Florian Müller is a postdoctoral researcher in the field of Human-Computer Interaction with a strong background in designing complex computer systems using C# and Java. His research interests focus on Augmented Reality, Virtual Reality and body-based concepts for interaction in and with the physical world. He received his Ph.D. in these areas at the Telecooperation Lab at the Technical University of Darmstadt and is currently working there as a lead of the Human-Computer Interaction group.

Work Experience

Postdoctoral Researcher and Group Lead

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DARMSTADT

• Leading the HCI research group of the Telecooperation Lab.

- Research on Urban Interaction in and with the physical World using Augmented Reality and Haptic Feedback.
- Teaching undergraduate and graduate students in the field of human-computer interaction.
- · Grant application proposal writing.

Ph.D. Student and Research Associate

Darmstadt, Germany

Darmstadt, Germany

Jan. 2020 - Today

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DARMSTADT

Apr. 2014 - Dec. 2019

- Technical and research lead of the Smart Spaces project, a joint project with the Electronics and Telecommunications Research Institute (ETRI) in Daejeon, South Korea.
- · Lead of the SoftwareCampus project NewViz with focus on visualization and interaction techniques for Big Data in collaboration with Software
- · Design, implementation, and analysis of a variety of controlled experiments and observational studies.
- Working on concepts for interaction with augmented interfaces on the go.

Education

Ph.D. in Human-Computer Interaction

Darmstadt, Germany

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DARMSTADT

2014 - 2019

• Thesis: Around-Body Interaction: Leveraging Limb-movements for Interacting in a Digitally Augmented Physical World. Graded with Summa Cum Laude (Highest Distinction)

M.Sc. in Computer Science

Darmstadt, Germany

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DARMSTADT

2011 - 2014

• Thesis: Developing an Interactive 3D Visualization for Video Monitoring Centers

B.Sc. in Computer Science

Darmstadt, Germany

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DARMSTADT

2008 - 2011

• Thesis: The Usage of Spatial Information of Viewers for Interactive Television Systems

Certificates & Awards

2020	Nominee, Outstanding Dissertation Award of the German Society for Computer Science (GI	Bonn, Germany
	Dissertationspreis)	Boini, Germany
2018	Graduate of development program for future IT executives, Software Campus with Software AG	Berlin, Germany
2019	Honorable Mention Award, CHI '19 - Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems	Glasgow, UK
2012	Best Paper Award, EuroITV '12 - European Conference on Interactive TV and Video	Berlin, Germany

Invited Talks_____

University of Hamburg, Mensch und Computer - Honored CHI Talks

Hamburg, Germany

Publications (Selection)

For a full list of 35+ publications, please see **₹**Google Scholar

2020	Around-Body Interaction: Leveraging Limb Movements for Interacting in a Digitally Augmented		
2020	Physical World , Dissertation. DOI: 10.1145/3290605.3300707		
2020	Around-Body Interaction: Interacting While on the Go , In IEEE Pervasive Computing, vol. 19, no. 02.	IFFF Pervasive	
2020	DOI: 10.1109/MPRV.2020.2977850	IEEE PEIVUSIVE	
2020	Walk The Line: Leveraging Lateral Shifts of the Walking Path as an Input Modality for HMDs, In Proc.	ACM CHI '20	
2020	2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. DOI: 10.1145/3313831.3376852	ACM CHI 20	
2019	Mind the tap: assessing foot-taps for interacting with head-mounted displays, In Proceedings of the	ACM CHI '19	
2019	2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. DOI: 10.1145/3290605.3300707	ACM CHI 19	

Teaching _____

2021	Hands-On HCI, Planning, preparation and giving lectures	Darmstadt, Germany
2016-201	9 Ubiquitous / Mobile Computing (Lecture) , Giving lectures and practical exercises	Darmstadt, Germany
2017	Human Computer Interaction (Lecture), Giving lectures	Darmstadt, Germany
2015	Foundations of Computer Science (Lecture), Organisation and preparation of practical exercises	Darmstadt, Germany
2016-202	0 Advanced User Interfaces (hands-on projects), Supervising Groups	Darmstadt, Germany
2014-202	0 B.Sc. and M.Sc. Theses , Supervised 25+ B.Sc. and M.Sc Theses	Darmstadt, Germany

Program Committees _____

	2020	Special Sessions Chair & Virtual Setup Chair , IEEE AIVR '20 - International Conference on Artificial	Utrecht, Netherlands
		Intelligence & Virtual Reality	otrecht, Netherlands
		Programm Comitee Member (Provocations and Works in Progess) , DIS '20 - ACM conference on	Eindhoven, Netherlands
	2020	Designing Interactive Systems	Emanoven, Netherlands
	2019	Programm Comitee Member (Short Papers), MUC '19 - Mensch und Computer	Hamburg, Germany
	2019	Workshop Organizer , Workshop on Interacting with Smart Objects in conjunction with EICS '19	Valencia, Spain
	2018	Workshop Organizer, Workshop on Interacting with Smart Objects in conjunction with CHI '18	Montréal, Canada
	2018	Workshop Organizer , Workshop on Ubiquitous Personal Assistance in conjunction with Ubicomp '18	Singapore
	2017	Workshop Organizer, Workshop on Interacting with Smart Objects in conjunction with IUI '17	Limassol, Cyprus
	2016	Workshop Organizer, Workshop on Interacting with Smart Objects in conjunction with IUI '16	Sonoma, CA, USA

Reviewing Activity _____

CHI	Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems	2017-2020
CHI Play	Annual Symposium on Computer-Human Interaction in Play	2019
DIS	Conference on Designing Interactive Systems	2018-2020
UIST	User Interface Software and Technology Symposium	2018
MuC	Mensch und Computer	2018-2020
MobileHCI	International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction with Mobile Devices and Services	2017-2020
IMWUT	Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies	2019-2020
ISMAR	International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality	2017-2019
SUI	Symposium on Spatial User Interaction	2017-2018

Skills_____

Programming Jav	va, C#, R, Dart	į
------------------------	-----------------	---

Research Design

Controlled experiments, observational studies, focus groups, (semi-) structured interviews

Quantitative Analysis

Qualitative Analysis

Open Coding, thematic analysis

Languages German, English